Currículum vítae

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Enrique Catalá Bañuls



Alicante (Alicante), Spain





@enriquecatala





www.enriquecatala.com

enrique@enriquecatala.com



https://es.linkedin.com/in/enriquecatala



https://github.com/enriquecatala

Sex Male | Date of birth 25/04/1981 | Nationality Spanish

BIO

Technical Leader at SolidQ, Computer Engineer, Microsoft Data Platform MVP and Microsoft Certified Trainer. My main role as Data Engineer is focused on the SQL Server relational engine. I'm passionate on solving performance problems in OLTP systems (database, dotnet and bare metal). Also specialized in the definition and implementation of reliable high availability environments in Azure and on premises, where I successfully led more than 150 projects not only in Spain but in different countries like USA ,United Arab Emirates, Netherlands, Mexico, Saudi Arabia, Austria... I'm the principal architect of the SolidQ solutions called HealthCheck, QueryAnalytics and DatabaseObfuscator. Regular speaker at SolidQ SUMMIT, member and speaker at SQL PASS in Spain and Latin America, staff member of the Madrid's SQLSaturday edition. I'm trying always to help people with both my personal GitHub account and the SolidQ Blog with my colleagues of SolidQ.

WORK EXPERIENCE

January 2020 - Present

Technical Leader

SolidQ (www.solidq.com)

- Be Azure DataPlatform evangelist with customers (by participating in public events)
- Be the people of contact with the customers that require advanced knowledge in the DataPlatform area
- Focus on get and maintain the edge of the technical knowledge in Azure and the data platform state, to share with my colleagues and help them achieve better
- To be part of the engineering team of some of the tools that SolidQ is levereaging internally to improve their services
- Help to achieve the best performance, scalability and security for the solution implemented to my customers
- Troubleshoot complex scenarios related with AO, replication, ServiceBroker, Clustering, Docker,...in both Azure and OnPremises deployments

January 2019 - 2020

Spain Relational Team Leader SolidQ (www.solidq.com)

- Understand my customers to end with the best architecture for their needs
- Create and manage the entire project portfolio with time, milestones, resources
- Help my sales team with successful engagements with customers
- Help my team to achieve the best implementation for the solutions they are working on (in the data platform area)
- Be a reference person when dealing on complex architecture designs/implementation that requires specific skills on the DataPlatform area

January 2008 – 2019

Mentor

SolidQ (www.solidq.com)

- Improve the ROI of the customer by improving their architecture
- Design and implementation of highly scalable and reliable OLTP solutions in critical systems (banking, insurance, online payment methods, e-commerce, ...).
- Performance and availability troubleshooting in critical 24x7 systems both at SQL Server level and client application (.NET)
- Design of advanced analytical solutions with machine learning (R and Analysis Services data mining, ...)
- Performance audits of .NET applications (backend mainly)
- Business intelligence projects with tabular technology (PowerBI with DAX)
- Architect and developer of QueryAnalytics and HealthCheck

April 2004 - January 2008

Data analyst

Tabimed S.A. (now part of www.bancosabadell.com)

Design and architecture of the data access layers for the main Applications

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

January 2020 - Present

Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Engineer Associate

Microsoft Certified: Solutions Associate: SQL 2016 Database

Administration

Expedited by Microsoft

2016 - Present

Microsoft Certified Solutions Expert: Data Management and

Analytics

Expedited by Microsoft

2015 - 2016

Master en Business Intelligence & Analitics con tecnologías

Microsoft

Focused on data analysis with R, data mining and scalable datawarehousing design for

Petabyte solutions.

2013 - Present

Microsoft Data platform MVP

Microsoft Data platform MVP since 2013. I'm one of the only 4 data platform MVP based

in Spain. This is my official profile.

For more info about the MVP program: https://mvp.microsoft.com/es-es/Overview

2013 - Present

Microsoft Certified Trainer

Expedited by Microsoft (yearly renewed since 2013).

2013 - Present

Microsoft Certified Solutions Expert

Expedited by Microsoft

Areas:

- Data Management and Analytics
- Data Platform

2013 - Present Microsoft Certified Solutions Associate

Expedited by Microsoft

2010 - Present Microsoft Certified IT Professional

Expedited by Microsoft

Database Developer and administration

2010 - Present Microsoft Certified Technology Specialist

Expedited by Microsoft

2004 Computer Engineer

Expedited by University of Alicante.

Honors obtained with my final master project called <u>modelado de objetos en almacenes de datos relacionales</u>.

PERSONAL SKILLS

Mother tongue Spanish, Catalonian

Ingles

Other language(s)

UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING
Listening	Reading	Spoken interaction	Spoken production	
C2	C2	C2	C2	C2

Nivel: A1/A2: usuario básico - B1/B2: usuario independiente - C1/C2: usuario competente Marco común Europeo de referencia para las lenguas

Communication skills

I worked for more than 150 companies while my focus is usually meeting with the CIO to explain how to achieve the best ROI and with the developers to help them built the new architecture. I have good communication skills acquired during my experiences as a national and international speaker in different big events such as Microsoft TechSummit, codemotion, SQL Pass, dotNetConference... where I have spoken in front of more than 500 people on several occasions. I'm involved in several projects that tipically ends with 2h/week meetings with USA customers (English)

Organizational /managerial skills

Leadership. Although at present I have personnel in charge in my company, it is frequent that in all the projects that I carry out, the customer puts me in charge of several of his own employees

Job-related skills

- ROI
- Data
- Performance tuning
- Reliable High availability solutions
- Azure data Platform
- Data platform migrations to Cloud
- Business Intelligence
- Languages commonly used
 - T-SQL, DAX, C#, python, PowerShell, PowerShell, M, R
- Other skills:
 - Multithread .net coding
- MVVM coding patterns
- Azure software integration
- Windows Universal Platform
- □ WCF
- □ XAML
- Good capacity for detecting inefficient architectures: Due to my extensive experience, I know design architectures that do not work in the long term.
- Transmission of knowledge: I am used to transmit knowledge to the people who work with me to make the team stronger

Other competences

Methodical and organized. Because in my current company I am in telecommuting (when I am not displaced to a client), I have acquired good habits of time control and organization

Driver license

A and B

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Microsoft oficial publications

- Implementación de un sistema de alta disponibilidad multisite con AlwaysON https://msdn.microsoft.com/es-es/sqlserver/dn393901
- Instalación de SQL Server paso a paso https://msdn.microsoft.com/es-es/sqlserver/gg521092
- Instalación de clusters SQL Server paso a paso http://msdn.microsoft.com/es-es/sqlserver/gg601099
- Instalación y configuración de SQL Server Integration Services paso a paso http://msdn.microsoft.com/es-es/sqlserver/gg690203
- Log shipping personalizado http://msdn.microsoft.com/es-es/sqlserver/hh291511
- Framework de administración declarativa http://msdn.microsoft.com/es-es/sqlserver/hh479546

Published books

- Planificando la migración de SQL Server 2000-2005 a SQL Server 2008 R2 (ISBN: 978-84-936417-9-5)
- Summit 2008 Madrid: Relational DB Track (ISBN: 978-84-936417-1-9)
- Planificando la migración de SQL Server 2000-2005 a SQL Server 2008 (ISBN: 978-84-936417-6-4)

Training material created

I'm the author of some international courses offered by my company. Some examples:

- Planes de ejecucion con SQL Server
- SQL Server Optimization, Performance Tuning and Troubleshooting
- Administración de SQL Server 2016
- Administración de SQL Server 2014
- ...

Projects

I work for companies under NDA, so I can not disclose the companies I work for. The sectors in which I work, usually are 24x7 open environments with business volumes of hundreds or thousands of millions of euros, and rely almost entirely on computer systems.

Banking, insurance, high-risk online payments, rental and booking of flights, naval management, are some of the sectors in which I usually work.

Speaker in conferences

National and international speaker at numerous events. Here some examples:

- Microsoft TechSummit: <u>Cortana Intelligence Suite: Datawarehouse como</u> <u>servicio en Azure (SQLDW)</u>
- SQL Saturday: Como leer planes de ejecución en SQL Server
- Codemotion: <u>Cómo hacer tuning a capas de acceso a datos .NET</u>
 Arquitecturas escalables en Azure: Mentiras y verdades

Here at my slideshare account you can find my last 42 conferences http://www.slideshare.net/enriquecatala

I'm also Vlogging at https://youtube.com/enriquecatala

Groups

- Member and co-founder of SQL Saturday Spain
- Member of Professional Association of SQL Server Professionals (PASS)

Attachments

- ExecutiveRecognitionLetter.pdf
 - Microsoft corporative vicepresident recognition letter.
- MS Learning Transcript.PDF
 - Full certification list